<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for vvomen: or, Womens defence. Pend by C.N. late of Albane Hall in Oxon</title>
            <author>C. N. (Christopher Newstead)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836955</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for vvomen: or, Womens defence. Pend by C.N. late of Albane Hall in Oxon</title>
                  <author>C. N. (Christopher Newstead)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[dward] G[riffin] for Ri. Whittakers: and are to be sold at his shop at the Kings head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.N. = Christopher Newstead.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Swetnam, Joseph.  The araignment of lewde, idle, froward, and unconstant women.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An apologie for women: or, Womens defence.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swetnam, Joseph, fl. 1617. --  Arraignment of lewd, idle, froward, and unconstant women --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1255:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1255:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> APOLOGY FOR VVOMEN: OR, <hi>Womens Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pend by <hi>C.N.</hi> late of Albane Hall in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>SOCRAT.</bibl> 
               <hi>Melius eſt mulieri non omnino naſci, quàm conuitijs lacerar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>Ri: Whittakers:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Kings head in Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1255:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1255:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT EXCELLENTLY VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady, MARY, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Buckingham, <hi>C. N. wiſheth euent of all felicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</hi> I neede not haue a Lanterne &amp; a Candle to inueſtigate a vertuous woman, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> had to finde an honeſt man: they appeare like ſo many Starres, fixed in this terreſtriall Globe. Yet no ſooner did the Sunne of your preſence enter into the Horizon of my thoughts, but it ouerſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed all the fore-appearers Honour ſeated in your breſt, findes it ſelfe adorned as in a rich Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, making that excellent,
<pb facs="tcp:1255:3"/>which makes it admirable, which cauſed me to preſent vnto your Ladiſhips protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this my ill-looking Infant, the maden-head (as I may ſo tearme it) of my inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conceiued in my brains, by the frothy word of many Hyperbolizing ſelfe-concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, who deeme it their greateſt grace, to be able to diſgrace women. If then (exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Lady) an ouer-ſpeedy or weaning deſire of repulſing your ſexes wrongs, hath cauſed my braines with <hi>Semele,</hi> to bring forth this obortiue Bacchus, or brood. Be you the <hi>Ioue</hi> to nouriſh it in the lap of your good liking, that being wrapt in the ſwaddling bands of your fauour, the cold of contempt may not ſo eaſily freeze it. And if <hi>Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> grant a ſafe returne to my Muſe traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king in her Indies, I ſhall, I hope, preſent you with a more richer Prize.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips vnfainedly deuoted in all obſeruant ſeruice, CH. NEVVSTEAD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1255:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, if thy tongue hath not tyed thee to a curſt wife, I doubt not, but the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall view of my Subiect, wil winne at the leaſt thy ordinarie acceptation. But when by peruſing, thou wouldſt eſpy how it is treated of, if thou beeſt illeterate, and the Curtaine of Ignorance be drawne before the eyes of thy Iudgement, I doe not much wey how thou art opinionated of me: if thou commend me,
<note place="margin">Miſere me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui mali ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid in me admiſerim. Petrar. de virt. opin.</note> I ſhal eſteeme (as <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> did, when he was praiſed of an euill one) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſe then better of my ſelfe: for <hi>quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid pene vulgus laudat, vituperio dignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt:</hi> Whatſoeuer ignorance co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth, moſt vſually deſerues to be diſcommended. I had rather with <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> the Poet haue the approbation of one iudicious <hi>Cato,</hi> then the applauſe of a multitude: the iudgements of the iudicious, and the vulgar,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2.</note> doe ſeldome iumpe. But if thou beeſt ſuch an one as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lius</hi> would haue his Auditour, neither igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb facs="tcp:1255:4"/>nor learned; Becauſe (ſaith hee) the one doth vnderſtand nothing, and the other more then I doe of my ſelfe. If thou beeſt, I ſay, lukewarme in knowledge, and that the <hi>Aurora</hi> of <hi>Minerua,</hi> the dawning of the day of literature, begins to twy-light thy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie; Iudge fauourably of the faults, that thy Eagle-eyed ſcrupuloſitie perceiues, they may bee errours of ignorance ſeene to thee: but they are an ignorance of the errours, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene to me. But if by the Ladder of induſtry (if any for the ſubiects ſake dare to credit) thou haſt aſcended the top of <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> I neede not tell thee, as the Poet ſaith of one, <hi>Nemo repentè fuit doctiſsimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection comes by degrees. <hi>Zeuxis</hi> his <hi>Helena</hi> was not ſuddenly lim'd forth with one Penſil: Braines to day are as empty, as <hi>Tellus</hi> his purſe of money, may to morrow, with <hi>Midas,</hi> be ſtuft with the gold of inuention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui non eſt hodie, cras magis aptus erit.</hi> Whatſoeuer thou art, vnleſſe thou be a Browniſt, I meane obſtinate, I doubt not, but it will perfume thy breath, for euer tainting women with reproches But thou wilt ſay, thy euill ſpeeches of them proceeds from mirth: thou mayſt as well ſay thou doſt lye with them, as belye them in test. No intentions
<pb facs="tcp:1255:4"/>can make abſolute euills good. Againe, ieſts ſhould be <hi>fecetoſi,</hi> not <hi>acetoſi;</hi> pleaſing, not piercing, neither continuall: therefore they are called <hi>ſales</hi> of the Latines, <hi>quaſi condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta;</hi> we ſhould vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Spices, to ſeaſon our talke, not as the ſubiect of it. But many may ſay with <hi>Philippus</hi> the Ieſter, that they haue got ſuch an habit in ſpeaking ill of them in ieſt, that they know not how to ſpeake well of them in earneſt. And it is a ſhrewd ſigne he neuer meanes well, that ſpeakes alwayes ill. But lest thou turne from them, to teſt on mee, for my prolixitie, in bidding mee (as <hi>Diogenes</hi> did the Citizens, that had excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ample gates, to a little Citie) ſhut the gates of my Preface, leſt the City of my Book runne forth, I will leaue thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, as thou vſeſt me.</hi> C. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1255:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1255:5"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY FOR VVOMEN: <hi>OR, Womens Defence.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Women in generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vi alium ſequitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſequitur,</hi> who makes alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples his Copie, ſhall many times erre from the rules of diſcretion. Should I tread in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1255:6"/>the ſteps of our preciſeſt Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts, in defining my Subiect, I might ſeeme with <hi>Didymus,</hi> to write that which each one knew, and giue a new teſtimonie of that old and highway <hi>Adage,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to burne Candle at noone day. For what ſo ignorant a <hi>Licinius,</hi> whoſe darke capacitie is not enlightened with this little candle of knowledge, to know what man is (for euery one knowes man in generall, though few in particular themſelues) from whom woman differs, onely in a materiall deſignation, hauing one and the ſame ſpecificall eſſence. Now the golden Ball, which their deſerts do challenge, is not honour, nor riches, nor beauty; but vertue. I ſtriue not to make them excell men, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did <hi>Pompey</hi> in digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or as the <hi>Lydeans</hi> Dames did their Husbands, in maſterie; but as <hi>Seneca</hi> did his Father, in vertue:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1255:6"/>
                  <hi>Haec ista honeſta contentio;</hi> this is an honeſt contention, or contentious honeſtie.</p>
               <p>It is true, at firſt, when there was but two actors, vpon this Theater of the world, woman was the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, that allured man vnto euill: but now each man with <hi>Tireſias,</hi> is metamorphoſed into a woman: pleaſures and delights, are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendring Serpents, that haue wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manized their affections: Men were the more perfect by nature: but wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men now then they, by induſtrie, (and it is more difficult to re-obtain vertue, then to keepe it.) <hi>Eue</hi> then tempted <hi>Adam,</hi> but now <hi>Adam</hi> tempts <hi>Eue:</hi> and it is better to bee conquered by Nature, then by Art. It is <hi>Catulus</hi> his ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that he could in thoſe things, which nature gaue to man, ſuffer patiently himſelfe to be ſubdued, but not in thoſe that might be aſſequuated, and got by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1255:7"/>our endeuours.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liu. Dec.</hi> 3.</note> For to be delinquent or faulty by nature, that is not ours, but natures fault; but to be ill by corruption, that is not natures, but our fault. VVhat if ſhe were an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſe of our fall, was ſhe not as much the cauſe of our riſing? But wee all ſooner forget benefits, then iniuries: we are Eagle-eyed in eſpying their faults, but dark ſighted Owles, in perceiuing their vertues. But not to make them all alike ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Dec.</hi> 3.</note> as <hi>Mantuan</hi> would haue them vicious, there are of women three ſorts: The firſt are thoſe who haue both a Theoreticall and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall knowledge of vertue by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Suct. l.</hi> 12:</note> vnderſtanding thoſe things that are good, and willingly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to effect them: and theſe may I condingly entitle, as the <hi>Romans</hi> did <hi>Titus, deliciae humani generis,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of mankinde:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paterc. pag.</hi> 125.</note> each one of theſe is a <hi>Scipio, qui nihil in vita niſi
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1255:7"/>laudandum, aut fecit, aut dixit,</hi> who neither ſpeake, nor doe any thing, but which is commendable; ſo apt to all goodnes, that they ſeeme with <hi>Cato</hi> to be borne to all actions they vndertake. The ſecond, are thoſe who though not ſo excellent, yet laudable: for although we maruell at the greateſt, yet wee praiſe thoſe that are leſſe:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. ep.</hi> 101.</note> 
                  <hi>non ſtatim ſtatim pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fillus eſt, ſi quis maximo minus eſt:</hi> hee is not preſently a Pigmy, that is leſſe then a gyant. In tranſcendent things thoſe are great, which are next to the beſt: thoſe, I ſay, who with <hi>Bici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> haue neede of one to direct them to goodnes; although they know not that which is honeſt by themſelues, yet they obey others rightly admoniſhing them, and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneri velle ſecunda virtus,</hi> it is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond vertue, to indure reprouing: for it argues a willingneſſe to bee good: and <hi>pars magna bonitatis est,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. Epiſt.</hi> 34.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1255:8"/>
                  <hi>velle fieri bonum:</hi> the next degree of goodnes, is the deſire of goodnes: theſe may I tearme,
<note place="margin">Diod. de Jamb.</note> as <hi>Plutarch</hi> doth <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> Camelions, from their facilitie of manners, whoſe mindes bend like the bones of the <hi>Iambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans,</hi> whither you will force them. <hi>Cereus in vitium flecti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horat. de Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Poet.</note> as the Poet ſaith of yong men, eaſie to bee drawne either to vertue, or vice. But <hi>natura ſuis neruis pulcherrìmum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euph. Sat. Apollo.</note> as perfect there is no ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly a body, in which doth not hang ſome clouds of corruption. <hi>Non datur ſincerum aliquod ſine mali admixtione:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phar. in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da Mar.</note> there is nothing ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere that hath not ſome admixtion of euill. In this <hi>Attica</hi> and pleaſing field of woman, there growe ſome Thiſtles among the Violets, and theſe are the third ſort, the dregges and ſcumme (as the Latines ſaid of the Romanes) of woman kinde: ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>Hera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>litcs,</hi> who neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1255:8"/>know good themſelues, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcend to others admonitions:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt. Eth. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> Theſe I exclude (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth them from his Ethicks) from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhield of my defence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though your foule-mouthed <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuans</hi> take occaſion to make theſe the Axeltree, on which the wheele of their tongues do continually run: who, becauſe their deſerts could neuer ſeate them in the fauour of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vertuous women, therefore they empty the dregs of their ſtomacks vpon all, with the Romans, for one Tyrannicall <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> to hate all Kings, like expert Logicians, out of particulars, concluding an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall. Aske them what woman is: and you ſhall haue them ſpeake contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction <hi>ex tempore:</hi> they are <hi>mala ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria,</hi> neceſſary euils: as though euill could be neceſſary: Since what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is needful, appertaines either to the <hi>eſse,</hi> or <hi>bene: Eſse</hi> of man, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1255:9"/>there is nothing neceſſary either to his eſſence or perfection that is ill. But leſt if I ſhould ſuffer the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of my wit to wander in the whole heauen of woman, and runne at randome in the ample field of their vertues, it might ſtray perhaps from the path way of Iudgement; I will now teather and confine it within the ground-plot of each of their particular qualities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their religious Piety.</head>
               <p>REligion meritoriouſly challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to act the firſt part of their praiſe:
<note place="margin">Oſorius lib. de Chriſti Nobilit.</note> and <hi>Oſorius</hi> tels me, that whom we would make immortall, we muſt proue religious.
<note place="margin">Hall.</note> Our <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda Sancti Brigit Hildegard,</hi> the firſt accuſers of the Romiſh Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; the learned ſiſter of <hi>Nazianzen, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Saluina Celantia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fox lib. de Mar.</note> Pillers of the Church: Holy <hi>Apollonia,</hi> whoſe ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1255:9"/>fire of zeale extinguiſhed the ſmart of this earthly and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary fire: <hi>Vrſula,</hi> who with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuen thouſand Virgins ſuffered Martyrdome, ſeeme to obiect enuy vnto me, in concealing theirs and innumerable other pieties: but, alas, I want not the will, but the power. The Poet bids me looke:
<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leant humeri?</hi> And I finde the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of my inuention too narrow to beare the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their due praiſes for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom. ad Il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. lib.</hi> 2.</note> If I had as many tongues as <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arius</hi> had hands, I could not enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate the praiſes due to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions: and it is better your pieties be conceal'd, then inſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueal'd; whiles we praiſe by halues, we diſgrace: an ill Inſtrument may ſhame a good worke: the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of the agent many times curſes a good enterpriſe. <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> his warres had better beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueloped
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1255:10"/>in obſcurity then diuulged by botching <hi>Labio;</hi> Truth is better hid, then wronged by telling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Continency and Chaſtity.</head>
               <p>COntinency is defined by the Prince of Philoſophers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o. Ethi. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Auſoni. hoc ſolum fecit nobile quod perut.</hi>
                  </note> when we immoderately deſire pleaſures, and yet abſtaine from them. This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition lookes like <hi>Otho</hi> his life, onely good in the end: the ſweet of it, which makes continency a vertue conſiſts as the honey of the Bee, in the Taile (for <hi>Vbicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deſines, ſi bene deſines tota eſt)</hi> too immoderately to deſire pleaſures, that argues weaknes: but to be able to caſt the cold aſhes of reſtraint, on the burning coles of deſires, that the ſtrongeſt vertue: the obiect then of continency is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in generall; giue mee leaue to reſtraine them onely to Veneriall.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1255:10"/>The firſt part of this vertue, <hi>viz.</hi> to immoderately deſire, I doubt not but the greateſt Myſogunians will grant vnto them: for the oracle of our beliefe doth teſtifie it, tearming them the weaker veſſels: and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe alwayes is the moſt ſubiect to gape after pleaſures, and in their bodies (if it may not ſeeme ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous) to adde the Sunne of verity the candle light of humane reaſon. Aire (ſaith the Philoſopher) doth predominate, and where moſt aire is, there is moſt <hi>Humidum radicale:</hi> being both of one nature, indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently hot and moiſt, where there is moſt <hi>Humidudum radicale,</hi> there is moſt ability of body, and where the body is moſt able, there naturally ſhould be moſt deſire.</p>
               <p>Now if any obiect as a fault,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tulli. de O ratore li.</hi> 1.</note> the natural proneneſſe of their bodies, <hi>Ciceroes</hi> anſwere to the Romans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing <hi>Murena</hi> to be conſul, becauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1255:11"/>he had liued in <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſhall be mine, telling them, that was not commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in <hi>Murena,</hi> that he had neuer ſeene, but that he had liued conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently in <hi>Aſia.</hi> What if their bodies be an <hi>Aſia,</hi> full of delights? that is not diſcommendable: but that their ſoules, a <hi>Murena,</hi> ſhould liue chaſte in the <hi>Aſia</hi> of their bodies, thats lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith of <hi>Leuanus</hi>) <hi>Hoc multo fortius ebrio ac vomitante populo ſobrium eſse;</hi> by this they are moſt vertuous, that their mindes ſhould be ſober, amongſt the rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous pleaſures of their bodies. It is the chiefeſt part of Continency, that it can, but will not doe ill. Now to proue their voluntary abſtinence from thoſe their deſires, examples muſt be my only <hi>Medium,</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they bee not demonſtrable arguments to proue a truth, yet they are probable, for (ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi>) <hi>vt habet in aetatibus authoritatem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nectus,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1255:11"/>ſic in exemplis antiquitas:</hi> ancient examples to preſent times ſhould be as venerable, as old age to youth.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. Epiſ.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Optimum ex praeterito conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium praeſentis venit,</hi> wee may beſt iudge of the preſent by things paſt. <hi>Lucretia,</hi> being asked of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, when <hi>Tarquinius</hi> had offered her violence, how ſhee did? anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liui. Deca.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid ſalum eſt multeri amiſsa pudicitia?</hi> What can be ſafe to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, when ſhee is bereaued of her chaſtity? The Romane Lady that neuer kiſt man, but her husband, did therefore deemed all men like vnto him, to haue obnoxious &amp; noyſom breaths. The Thebane maide, before <hi>Nicanor</hi> ſhould be the caruer vp of her virginity, choſe to be her owne boiſtrous Butcher. Our <hi>Matilda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Speed Chron.</note> ere ſhe would aſſent to the vnlawfull ſute of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> fled to a Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and there ſuffered death. And what was the reaſon that the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1255:12"/>conſtituted them the mouthes of their Oracles, and gouernors of their Temples, but for their chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſanctity? and whoſoeuer ſhall read hiſtories, or looke into theſe preſent times, ſhall find many chaſte <hi>Orythyas,</hi> for one <hi>Carneades,</hi> many continent <hi>Clea's</hi> for one <hi>Socrates,</hi> and on the contrary many a laſciuious <hi>Caligula,</hi> for one <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> many an incontinent <hi>Tiberius,</hi> for one <hi>Liuia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> but that which giues the moſt luſter of their continency, is, that men who as I haue proued ſhould be natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt chaſte, are aſſailants, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they ſhould bee defendants: but now cuſtome hath made it no fault in them, for <hi>Multitudo peccantium tollit peccatum,</hi> the multitude of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders takes away the offence, and faults are no longer feared, then that they are rare, but our Engliſh ſo <hi>Seneca</hi> tels them,
<note place="margin">Halt.</note> that offences are much greater, as they are more vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1255:12"/>Do they not obſerue houres, dayes, and all occaſions, to batter the wailes of their chaſtity? And what will not importunity and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity effect? which as they ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate the fault in the agent, ſo they extenuate, though not excuſe it in the patient. Certainely, if they ſhould vſe the like meanes, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine men, a Nay would bee as ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as treaſon in the mouthes of moſt men. Yet ſo iniurious are the cenſures of theſe our times, that if a <hi>Ioue</hi> vanquiſh but, or vitiate or in or in vanquiſhing, viciate a ſilly <hi>Io,</hi> a graue <hi>Cato,</hi> a light or tender Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, black infamy ſhall ouercloud, and brand her reputation, not once touching his.
<note place="margin">Juuena. Sat.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ille pretium ſceleris,</l>
                  <l>tulit hic Diade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a.</l>
                  <l>Of he fault poore ſhe</l>
                  <l>ſhall beare the blame,</l>
                  <l>When he's crown'd with</l>
                  <l>a Diadem.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1255:13"/>
               <p> As ſweetely ſings a Lady in our Engliſh <hi>Ouid.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Drayton Poet.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>To men is granted</l>
                  <l>priuiledge to tempt:</l>
                  <l>But in that Charter,</l>
                  <l>women be exempt:</l>
                  <l>Their fault it ſelfe</l>
                  <l>ſerues for the faults excuſe,</l>
                  <l>And makes it ours,</l>
                  <l>though yours be the abuſe:</l>
                  <l>And howſoeuer,</l>
                  <l>although by force they win,</l>
                  <l>Yet on our weakeneſſe,</l>
                  <l>ſtill returnes the ſinne.</l>
               </q>
               <p>If women bee vnchaſte,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jncontinem ſemi-malus Ariſt. Ethi. l.</hi> 7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Continentia melior Tem. Ariſt. Ethi. l.</hi> 7.</p>
                  </note> they are but incontinent, and therefore but <hi>ſemi-malae,</hi> but halfe euill: If man be vnchaſte, he is vntemperate, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>totaliter malus,</hi> wholy euil, if they be both chaſte, ſhee is continent, and he but temperant, and therefore more to be praiſed:
<note place="margin">Sene Epiſ.</note> for <hi>Quamuis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundem finem vterque peruenerit, tamen maior est laus, idem efficere dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiliore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1255:13"/>materia:</hi> although they both attaine the ſame end, yet it is the more laudable to effect the ſame in a more difficult matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Fortitude and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity.</head>
               <p>ALthough continency bee the beſt fortitude, and it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt conqueſt, when the body is the Chariot, that carries the minde tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing ouer its affections: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Laelius</hi> told his friend,
<note place="margin">Liui. deca.</note> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared with the beauty of <hi>Syphax</hi> his wife, that it would be a more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble victory, to conquer his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to her, then in ſubduing the husband: <hi>Maximum eſt imperium im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare ſibi,</hi> and he is moſt valiant that conquers himſelfe: yet becauſe you ſhall not deeme them inferiour to you in warrelike fortitude, take <hi>Seneca's</hi> iudgement of them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. ca.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Quis
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1255:14"/>dixerit naturam maligne cum mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus egiſse, par illis mihi crede vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, &amp;c.</hi> who ſaith, that nature hath giuen her fauours ſparingly to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, they haue the ſame vigour, and can, as well tolerate labours, as men, if they be accuſtomed to them. To omit the men-conquering <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons,</hi> there is none I know ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, to whom the trumpet of fame hath not blowne their valors.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Xerx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> (he that was alwayes laſt in the field, and firſt out) ſeeing <hi>Artemiſia</hi> brauely fighting amongſt his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, ſayd (for euen the vicious thinke well of vertue) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s there is in man womaniſh feare, ſo there is in woman virill auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
               <p>The Romanes had no leſſe fight with the women,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> then with their husbands, in conquering the <hi>Cim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brians Semiramis</hi> receiuing ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1255:14"/>ſpeeches from the King of the <hi>Indians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>orus de antiqui.</note> renunciated and ſent him word, ſhe intended not to fight with words, but with ſwords.
<note place="margin">Cam. Brit.</note> The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent inhabitants of this Ile, the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, <hi>Vaodicia</hi> being their General, ſhaked off the Romane yoke, and moſt of their proſperous battels were when women did leade them.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tus Anna.</hi> 4.</note> And was not <hi>France</hi> wholy ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne by our Engliſh,
<note place="margin">Grim. his Fran.</note> vntill (as the French brag) that valorous <hi>Ioane</hi> gaue life to the French, confron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our braue <hi>Bedford</hi> in the field? And what was the Phoenix of her time, our euer to bee renowned Queene, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> at whoſe frowne Kings trembled? And that fiery-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited <hi>Blanch,</hi> Dutches of <hi>Orlean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> when King <hi>Philip</hi> had giuen her diſgracefull words, replyed, that if (to vſe my authors words) ſhe had a paire of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Fren. Hiſt.</note> hee durſt not ſo haue reuiled her. But thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1255:15"/>they may haue couragious minds, but they want force. Oh! men are ſtronger then they. So are many beaſts ſtronger then men,
<note place="margin">Senc.</note> 
                  <hi>Corpus ſi magnas habet vires, non aliter quam furioſi validum eſt:</hi> Valour conſiſts in the minde, not in the body; not Megaſomity, but Magnanimity, is the vertue: it is the minde that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols deiected things, illuſtrates baſe things, dehoneſtates great things. They yeeld to men to haue windes like <hi>Dionyſius</hi> that ſtrong-ſided Trumpeter,
<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>us Hiſt.</note> who with his breath could puffe about Wind-Mils.</p>
               <p>So that they haue minds able to blow away all baſe feares:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. l.</hi> 3.</note> And what more euident ſigne of their valor, then their loue of it? <hi>Homer</hi> indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>Helena</hi> complaining of <hi>Hymen,</hi> that hee had eſpouſed her to one, who durſt not defend her againſt the enemy. The <hi>Laconians</hi> ſeeing their huſbands feare, lending them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1255:15"/>wings to flye from the field, asked them if they intended to obſcond themſelues in their mothers bellies? <hi>Tiphane</hi> perceiuing her beloued <hi>Bertrand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fren. hi.</note> for the ſweet of her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, to let his deſire of Martiall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires quaile within him; told him ſhe ſhould the entirelier loue him, if he did ſtil proſecute the honour and reputation of Chiualry.
<note place="margin">Draſm. Rhetor.</note> 
                  <hi>Damatria</hi> her ſonne complaining of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſword, bid him ſtand neerer his enemy. <hi>Venus</hi> did more affect bloudy <hi>Mars,</hi> then timorous &amp; fairefac't <hi>Apollo.</hi> And how many <hi>Katherines</hi> choſe rather to bee cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with conquering Launces, then Court-like Rapters? I might heere <hi>a poſteriore</hi> (as the Logicians tearme it) from the effects inferre their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, women beeing the cauſe of that <hi>calor caeleſtis,</hi> the heauenly fire of loue, which burnes, as it did in <hi>Lepidus,</hi> all ignoble, and ſeruile
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1255:16"/>feares from mens hearts, the whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone (as one ſaith of Anger) that exacuates and ſets an edge on mens obtuſe and blunt affections: the <hi>Lapis Alchimicus,</hi> the Philoſophers Stone, that conuerts Leaden paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, into any golden ſweet content: but that many pens haue teſtified the ſame, and I am loth to bee a Broker of other mens wits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their conſtancie and true loue.</head>
               <p>THere is a greater Sympathy of affections in friendſhips, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, betwixt man &amp; woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then man and man. For you ſhall not reade of aboue foure or fiue couples of men that were linkt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the bands of faithfull friendſhip, when Authors ſwarme with ſexamples betwixt the other. <hi>Similitudo morum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 250.</note> the ſimilitude of affections, as <hi>Otho</hi> obtained <hi>Neros,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1255:16"/>is the cauſe of virall friendſhip: but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nature it ſelfe, is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of coniugall friendſhip. It is <hi>Iucunda amicitia,</hi> that is the cauſe of this <hi>vera amicitia.</hi> It is pleaſure, that tyes the indiſſoluble knot of true friendſhip; delight begins it, hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie confirmes it: for where pleaſure is, there is deſire of ſocietie, and thats the key, that locks their thoughts together. Shee then that is eſpouſed to one whom ſhee doth not affect, if ſhee loue another, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not be ſaid to be inconſtant, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent. For inconſtancie is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of conſtancie: they muſt then firſt loue, ere they bee incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. If then (courteous Reader) thou doeſt but ballance the ſcales of thy iudgement with impartiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, duely waying the nature of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie, thou wilt not hereafter ſo raſhly accuſe them of inſtable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. What if there be one <hi>Helena</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1255:17"/>amongſt all the Graecians; one <hi>Liuia</hi> amongſt all the Romans; one <hi>Cleopatra</hi> amongſt all the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: wilt thou therefore ſhoot the arrow of thy fame-wounding iudgement againſt all, the Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Romanes and Egyptians? There is no motion, but circular, that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes perfect. All are not Starres, fixed in the Orbe of conſtancie, there muſt bee ſome ſtraying Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſt. l.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Eliſa</hi> Queene of Carthage, her Husband being murdered, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward beeing ſollicited of many for her loue, praecipitated her ſelfe from a Sky-kiſsing Turret,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſt. l.</hi> 18.</note> ſaying, I come, my <hi>Sychaeus,</hi> I come. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena,</hi> wife to <hi>Agathocles,</hi> refuſed to depart from him, when all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects had relinquiſht and forſaken him, ſaying, <hi>Se non proſperae tantum, ſed omnis fortunaeiniſſe ſocietatem,</hi> ſhe was as wel married to him in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, as in proſperitie. And not to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1255:17"/>ſtand particularizing,
<note place="margin">Diod.</note> the Getoi wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would not be ſent from their husbands beſieged: but would par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of the ſame fortune they did.
<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od.</note> It beeing a cuſtome amongſt the Indians, that the women ſhould be buried quick with their husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, if the thred of their liues were firſt cut, they ſo willingly condiſcended vnto it, that many times one man hauing two wiues, they would be at mortall ſtrife, who ſhould be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him. <hi>Martia,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Cato,</hi> being demanded when ſhe would ſurceaſe from mourning for her deceaſed husband, <hi>Cum &amp; vitae inquit:</hi> When I ceaſe to liue. The wife of <hi>Philo,</hi> when ſhee was asked why ſhee did not adorne her ſelfe with Iewels at publike ſolemnizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, anſwered, It ſufficeth me, that I haue for my ornament the vertue of my husband. The Wife of <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> ſlew her ſelfe vpon his dead
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1255:18"/>corps, from whom, I thinke, the Tragedian took his ſentence,
<note place="margin">Sen. Trag.</note> 
                  <hi>Mors miſera non eſt, commori cum quo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Pale death to life</l>
                  <l>is oft of thoſe preferd,</l>
                  <l>Who are with thoſe,</l>
                  <l>whom they doe loue, interr'd.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Should I ſtand to enumerate all the regular Matrons that mooue within the ſpeare of fidelitie; I might ſeeme by a Logicall Inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in reckoning vp all particulars, to inferre a generall. Women, their mindes are cryſtall, which writ on by the Diamond of loue, the ſlub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering fingers of Time can neuer obliterate or blot forth: Like the ſtate of the world aboue the Moon, where there is no change. Their minds perhaps, as (<hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith) a wiſe mans, may wauer, but neuer alter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1255:18"/>
               <head>Of their contempt, and freeneſſe from Gluttonie.</head>
               <p>THere is none, I thinke,
<note place="margin">Rick. Rhet.</note> ſo ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſly malicious, vnleſſe hee reſemble the Philoſopher, who doubted whether he were a man or a woman, and therefore would haue it decided by diſputation, that will ſuffer any thought to mooue within the Zodiake of there imaginations, which doth not in this giue Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the preeminence. Peruſe thou all Authors, that haue in there writings diſgorged and ſpet forth their venemous rancour againſt them: and if thou canſt finde two of them that were addicted to Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrimorgiſme, I will grant thee to inferre that they are all diſhmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, when the ſtreame of Autors beares floting on their Pageants, innumerable mens names, who by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1255:19"/>brought both bodies and purſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſumptions. <hi>Philoxenus</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his necke were as long as a Cranes, that hee might the longer feele the ſweetnes of his meat: and he <hi>(qualis vita, finis ita)</hi> hauing taken a mortall ſurfet, by deuouring almoſt a <hi>Polypus</hi> of the quantitie of two Ells, deſired to comfort his empty ſtomack, that death ſhould ſeparate his leane ſoule, from his fat body, that he might eat the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aclian. l.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Sminderides,</hi> whoſe eyes were ſixe times as long ſhut with Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, as <hi>Endymions</hi> was with ſleepe, from beholding the Sunne, and then forſooth by Loue, being awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked from his ſluggiſhnes, he rode a wooing, brauely attended with a thouſand Cookes, as many Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and ſo many Fiſhers. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Nero's</hi> ſhall you finde banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſwilling, from midday, to midnight, with <hi>Vitellius,</hi> making (as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1255:19"/>one ſaith) their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and <hi>honeſtum et parum eſt, cui corpus multum,</hi> whoſe belly is his god, honeſtie moſt commonly is his ſlaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their dextericall Wits.</head>
               <p>IF the acuteneſſe of wit doe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and be ſeene by the purenes of the temperature of the body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as without doubt it is: for it heere is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the moſt exact ſenſe of feeling and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſoft temperate fleſh, where there is a ſmirke and quicke wit: women (being they are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly imbued with thoſe corporall fauours) ſhould by a conſequent bee the beſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, haue the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and excelling wits: and when <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> prefer's the more obtuſe and melancholy wit, before the dextericall; it is in affaires where
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1255:20"/>there is time for deliberation: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies the prae-wit excels the poſt wit, as actions performed in ſeaſon, doe thoſe which are out of ſeaſon. For many times, when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is offered the prae-wit takes it by the forehead, when the other whiles the time away it: doth ſearch the corners of the braines, for the oyle of inuentions, ſtayes till the doore of anſwering be ſhut againſt it: Like the meſſenger that came to tell <hi>Caſsius</hi> of the victory,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paterc. pa.</hi> 122.</note> when hee had already ſlaine himſelfe in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of it:
<note place="margin">Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us.</note> and <hi>elleborum fruſtra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umiam cutis aegra tumebat.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>In vaine we to inuention flye,</l>
                  <l>When occaſion's paſt, for to reply.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> tearmeth perſpicuitie of wit, <hi>aurum diuinum,</hi> diuine and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined gold, whoſe Mine is the minde of a woman: And therefore the Muſes, the fountaine of all wit, were women: The Sybils, <hi>quarum
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1255:20"/>quot verba, tot Oracula,</hi> whoſe words as an Oracle to the Romanes, were women. The quinteſſence, the A <hi>per ſe</hi> (as one ſaith of Poets) of wit:
<note place="margin">Aeneas Syl.</note> the euen flowing <hi>Euripus</hi> of faculty, learned <hi>Sapho,</hi> a vvoman. The daughter of <hi>Tully</hi> being asked in ſcurrility, by <hi>Metellus</hi> who was her Father? replyed, It would be hard for thee to anſwere it, by reaſon of thy Mother, (for ſhee was eſteem'd none of the honeſteſt.) It vvas a pretty extemporarie ſleight of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marimus:</hi> who,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 7.</note> when the Indian King cauſed her to aſcend his Throne, and gaue her authority to command the Souldiours, to doe what ſhe would; ſhe preſently bid them kill the King himſelfe: and ſo ſhe obtained his Kingdome. And whoſe eye is not blinded with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignitie, may ſee the floud of their wits ſtill to flow in theſe our times.</p>
               <p>It is a more then probable ſigne,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1255:21"/>that they excell men in the actiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wit, in that (as I haue proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) they are leſſe incident to Gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandizing:
<note place="margin">Lab. in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and as a modern Poet pithy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Engliſheth:
<q>
                     <l>Fat panches make leane pates,</l>
                     <l>and groſer bits</l>
                     <l>Enrich the ribs,</l>
                     <l>but bankrout quite the wits.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Wiſedome.</head>
               <p>PErſpicuitie of wit is of the Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifts made the chiefeſt part of wiſedome,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mag. in Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ. l.</hi> 3.</note> differing ſolely from it: as <hi>pars</hi> doth a <hi>toto:</hi> as the part from the whole. Indeed, wiſedome is nothing but a perfected wit, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely neceſſary by nature: the other parts got by experience. If then women haue actiueneſſe of wit, reaſon will tell you, they moſt eaſily attaine to prudence, which is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1255:21"/>(becauſe the knife of occaſion, will not ſuffer me to ſhred it into all his parts) either Oeconomicall, or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall. Concerning the firſt, the whole multitude cryes, as they doe to Kings, <hi>Regnant, regnant:</hi> Let it appertaine to the Sexe feminine to gouern the houſe, and ſo their poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes prudence, who knowes how to guide a little, will quickly learn how to gouerne much. Our politike Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſprung firſt, from Oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. And <hi>domus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle) eſt quaſi parua quae dam ciuitas, &amp; ciuitas quaſi magna domus:</hi> a houſe is, as it were a little Citie, and a Citie, as it were, a great houſe. But let one, vvho with <hi>Diogenes</hi> could neuer afford woman a good vvord, ſpeake for them, ſaying, that nature had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied vnto them ſtrength: for other wiſe, their courage beeing corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by policy, would bee vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable. <hi>Antipater</hi> vvas accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1255:22"/>vvith his Daughter <hi>Phila,</hi> to conſult of his moſt ſerious and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affaires.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Tannaquill,</hi> that poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Romane Dame, obtained by the ſleyts of her wits, two Empire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. <hi>Agrippina,</hi> when al the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines could not aſſwage the raging of the people,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 6</note> with her ſweet and Nectar-flowing words of vvit, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and pacified them. <hi>Heluna,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Seneca,</hi> was expert in all Sci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce: The Armenians expulſed their King, to haue a VVoman ſway the Scepter of their Monarchy: ſhewing, that there are women both more wiſe to iudge vvhat is to bee expected,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and more conſtant to beare it when it is hapned. But I may ſay of their vertues, as one ſaith of vices;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Multarum latent virtutes, quia imbecilles ſunt,</hi> the clouds of obſcuritie, many times ouerſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow the Sunne of their Vertues from ſhining: and <hi>haud diſtat iner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1255:22"/>caelcita virtus.</hi> Vertue concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is eſteemed little better then ſluggiſhnes. They may haue nature vvhich begins; Art which directs; but they want vſe, which per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecteth. <hi>Generoſos animos Otium corrumpit:</hi> vvant of imployment, corrupts the braueſt ſpirits; the fountain of their vertue, corrupts by ſtanding. Want of vſe, cauſeth diſabilitie; but cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, perfection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Beauty.</head>
               <p>ALthough it bee a Tenent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Stoicks (who would haue men impaſſionate,
<note place="margin">Diad. l. de Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>q.</note> &amp; without affections, as <hi>Diodorus</hi> writes of ſome Arabians) that there is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall good, addes perfection to a man: Yet the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> hold them, although not neceſſarie, yet requiſite, as one diſtinguiſheth, not abſolute: <hi>ſed reſpectiue,</hi> they doe not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1255:23"/>concurre to perfection,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but as it is mans perfection: and of all aduentitiall, and extrafi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call goods, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> giues the principalitie to pulchritude, which doth not cauſe vertue, but graceth it. <hi>Plutarch</hi> accuſeth <hi>Seneca</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Iudgement, in that he accuſeth <hi>Virgil</hi> of errour, in ſaying that <hi>Gratior est pulchro veniens ecor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore virtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Plac't with beauty, vertue's like</l>
                  <l>Rich Pearle ſet in a Margarite.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non ſatis eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Galatcus) bene quid facere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cal. de Mor.</note> 
                  <hi>niſi etiam fiat venustè.</hi> It is not ſufficient to performe actions ſo vvel,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> vnleſſe alſo decently. <hi>Sumus omnes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Oſorius) natura concin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tatis, appetentes:</hi> wee all naturally deſire neatnes, &amp; concinnity. Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is call'd of <hi>Plato,</hi> a prerogatiue of nature, accidentall to few: Of <hi>Theophraſtus, ſilentem fraudem, quod abſque verbis perſuadebat:</hi> a ſilent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1255:23"/>fraud, that perſwades without words. Of <hi>Carneades,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a Kingdome without a guard; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it commands without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion. And therefore ſaith the Philoſopher, If there were any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the gods, that did excell in externall lineaments, the reſt would deeme it meet that they ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The <hi>Catharri</hi> choſe them to be libertie free, who were of a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proportion, the reſt they made ſeruile.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And if I may not come within the reach of <hi>Iuuenals</hi> laſh, the <hi>primus Motor,</hi> the abſtract of faireneſſe, entitled (with reuerence be it ſpoken) his Spouſe in the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> by the name of faire: Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Adamantine and winning power it hath, with mortals. For beeing the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of each obiect, &amp; impreſſed in the ſence, before it bee in the vnderſtanding, it is a good conſequent, that whatſoeuer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1255:24"/>is moſt delightfull tothe Organical ſences, the Intellectuall parts are moſt willing to receiue. I neede not ſet inuention on the racke, to proue their Prerogatiue in corporall fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as I haue in their internall and mentall forme, ſince our ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eyes doe more eaſily ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, then our intelligible vnderſtand. I haue need of a <hi>Sapho's</hi> wit, to deſcribe the Roſe of their beauty; not an <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> Iudgement, to proue it. Let each ones ſences bee the glaſſe, in which they view beauty; and then, I thinke, there will be none ſo hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, or falſe, that will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexe ſome ſhaddow of their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chritude, by which they may ſee them to ſurpaſſe men. <hi>Quantum len. ta ſolent inter viburna Cupreſsi,</hi> as much as the lofty Cypreſſe doth ouerpeere the limber ſhrubbe: or,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Achil. Tac. lib.</hi> 8.</note> as one ſaith of <hi>Epheſius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as faire
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1255:24"/>not amongſt, but aboue men; as <hi>Rodope,</hi> aboue the Virgins. The Craſis of their bodies, comes nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the Phyſicians <hi>temperamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad pondus.</hi> Although ſelfe-tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting enuie, which alwaies, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ignis ſummapetit,</hi> a perpetuall companion of vertue, ſeek to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geale vapours in the sky of beauty, with the noiſomneſſe of its breath, by obiecting incontinence vnto it, as a Poet ſings:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>There is no name</l>
                  <l>(if ſhe be falſe or not,)</l>
                  <l>But being faire,</l>
                  <l>ſome enuious tongue will blot:</l>
               </q>
               <p>As if nature were an Hypocrite, to candie ouer the bitter Pils of the minde, with ſugred outſides. No, no, their externall feature doth ſtriue (as <hi>Paterculus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Victinius</hi>) with the excellencie of their mindes; whoſe vertues being a Iewell, inveloped in the ſiluer O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1255:25"/>of their bodies, like <hi>Achilles,</hi> of whom <hi>Maximus Tarrhus</hi> ſaith, Not onely to bee extold for her golden looks, but becauſe he was adorned with all vertuous qualities.
<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ge. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The cord of ſociety (as <hi>Chryſippus</hi> nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates it) or pulchritude, is deſcribed to bee a proportionable commixti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the foure elements in mans body, &amp; where no one element doth predominate in the body, there no one paſſion doth captiuate the ſoule:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for, <hi>Cuius in vllo elementi por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio praeualebit, inde moris erunt,</hi> the minde deriues his paſſions from the preuailing clement in the body: where <hi>Frigidity</hi> doth predominate, their t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>morouſnes; where <hi>Calidity,</hi> there choler: wherfore <hi>Plato</hi> would haue children prohibited, and yong men in the hot Meridean of their age, to abſtaine from Wine, becauſe by califying the body, it inflameth alſo the minde.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1255:25"/>
               <p> And whereas we ſee many with <hi>Lepidus,</hi> to haue fairer bodies then minds, leaden Rapiers, in golden Sheathes, like <hi>Diogenes</hi> young man, a <hi>Momus</hi> wit in an <hi>Apello's</hi> body, like <hi>Nereus</hi> Beard in a painted Box, it is not by the inſtinct of nature, but by the corruption of it: and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when wee ſee many golden qualities placed, as <hi>Aeſops</hi> Iewell, in in the dunghill, in Leaden bodies, as in <hi>Galba,</hi> of whome <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid, his wit had an ill lodging; nature doth not imbue them with them, but induſtry obtaines them, as <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and our laſt Cardinall confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of themſelues, The temperature of the body doth but beginne and inchoate our affections, cuſtome and vſe are of moſt validity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore generally wee may iudge, as an Epigrammatiſt doth of a ſlow pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Lordane:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1255:26"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Tardus es ingenio,</l>
                     <l>vt pedibus, natura etenim dat</l>
                     <l>Exterius ſpecimen,</l>
                     <l>quod latet interius.</l>
                     <l>Thy leaden heeles</l>
                     <l>no golden wit doe ſhew:</l>
                     <l>For in-bred gifts</l>
                     <l>by outward limbs we know.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their comfort to man.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing more oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to mans nature, then ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: and therefore he is deſcribed to be <hi>animal ſociale,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ven. epiſ.</hi> 10</note> a ſociable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: it is one of the two by which he hath his prerogatiue of beaſts, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietas illi dominum animalium dedit:</hi> Company hinders from many of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, when <hi>Omnia nobis mala ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo perſuadit,</hi> Solitarineſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades to all euill. <hi>Crates</hi> ſeeing a young man ſpaciating by himſelfe, demanded what he did there alone?
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1255:26"/>
                  <hi>Mecum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>loquor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> I talke with my ſelfe. Take heed then, replied <hi>Crates,</hi> leſt <hi>cum homine malo loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> thou conferreſt with an euil one. It is better for a man to be with any one, then with himſelfe. Art thou with <hi>Metelius</hi> in proſperity, and doth Fortune, with a proſperous gale of winde, blow the Ship of thy life towards the Port of riches? thou canſt neuer by thy ſelfe, without the cords of friends, caſt Anker in the Hauen of contentednes: for <hi>Nullius boni ſine ſocietate iucunda poſſeſsio eſt:</hi> There is no pleaſing poſſeſſion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing without a companion. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, art thou with <hi>Rutilius</hi> in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: &amp; doth the bluſtring Boreas of miſ-fortune, caſt thee on the rock of pouerty? yet <hi>ſolamen miſeris,</hi> the comfort of friends is comfort: it is a ſweete thing in aduerſity to haue, who laments with vs our miſeries; <hi>vt ſerenitas gratior in tempeſtate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lip. epiſ.</hi> 62.</note>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:1255:27"/>
                  <hi>ſic lugenti amico amicus,</hi> as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity to Mariners after tempeſts; ſo the Sunne-ſhine of a friends pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, is moſt gratefull to his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relatiue, in the tempeſt of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity: <hi>Lacrimis lacrimis miſcere iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. Helena</hi> could tell <hi>Hecuba,</hi> that her ſorrow was light in reſpect of hers, becauſe ſhe had coopartners in it: for <hi>magis exurunt, quos ſecretae lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant curae.</hi> Care doth moſt ſcorch, when we pen it within the narrow compaſſe of our owne hearts. Wel then, there is no true ioy, without a friend, and no friend, in reſpect of a wife, a woman to a man, who, if thou beeſt iocund, ads pleaſure to thy mirth, and makes the cup of thy heart ouerflow with the nectar of delight. Art thou ſad, and doth care gnaw thy perplexed minde? why, <hi>Eſt aliquod fatale malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba leuari,</hi> by words thou muſt eaſe it: and who ſo conuenient as a wife
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1255:27"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o vnclapſe the boſome of thy thoughts vnto? who either bedew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her cheeks with teares for the, beares halfe thy burthen, or elſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterging or wiping with her ſoft hand teares from thy eyes, as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from thy ſoule, as <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocaſta</hi> did to <hi>Oedipus</hi> with a conſolatory,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>. nal.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. pro vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Deca.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid ur uat, coniux, mala grauare quastu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>What helpes it, Sweet,</l>
                     <l>to aggrauate</l>
                     <l>By ſorrow thy</l>
                     <l>diſaſtrous fate?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>What a Patheticall Oration makes <hi>Meſſalinus</hi> for women, to aſſociate their husbands in the wars in forraine regions? <hi>Quod honeſtius, quam leuamentum vxortum reuerten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus poſt laborem, &amp;c?</hi> what more conuenient, then to haue, when wee returne from our labours, then the comfort of our wiues,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as that one eye of <hi>Minerua</hi> teſtifieth of them?</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:1255:28"/>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt finde</l>
                  <l>in women vertues lie:</l>
                  <l>Sweote ſupple minds,</l>
                  <l>which ſoone to vertue bow,</l>
                  <l>Where they, by wiſedomes rule</l>
                  <l>directed are,</l>
                  <l>And are not forſt</l>
                  <l>fond thraldome to allow.</l>
                  <l>As we to get are fram'd,</l>
                  <l>ſo they to ſpare:</l>
                  <l>We made for paine,</l>
                  <l>they made, our paines to cheriſh,</l>
                  <l>We care abroad,</l>
                  <l>and they at home haue care.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I may ſay of them,
<note place="margin">Euri. Trag.</note> as <hi>Euripides</hi> ſaith of the iuſt man, They ſeeme <hi>non ſibi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pet. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emr. ſortu.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed alijs natae,</hi> not to be borne to themſelues, but to others. <hi>Dulces parentes, dulces fillij, dulces fratres, dulces amici, ſed dulciſsimae vxores.</hi> It is a ſweet thing to haue parents, children, brothers and friends, but it is moſt amoene, it is moſt ſweete, to haue the comfort of a louing wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1255:28"/>when parents proue vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, children rebllious, brothers vnkind, friends vnconſtant, wiues are onely like the Gemelli of <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> inſeparable; the ſweete that muſt reliſh all thoſe ſowre potions: a wife is as a good conſcience to a man, whereſoeuer ſhe is, there is true peace and ioy: a man is neuer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, vntill he be married, till then he is defectiue, he wants a Ribbe, not <hi>vxor fulgit</hi> (as the Ciuilian ſaith) <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs mariti, ſed maritus radijs vxoris:</hi> She is as the Sunne, and hee the Moone, the beames of her preſence is the cauſe of his ſhining. It may be an Axiome as well as an Adage, <hi>Verberat vxorem qui non habet:</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married men only beat their wiues, who diſcommend them out of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance for wee cannot iudge of ſweet, vntill we taſte them: but moſt maligne them, as <hi>Appius</hi> did <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> becauſe they cannot obtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1255:29"/>them: and married men diſlaude them, becauſe they haue them: for <hi>Quicquid domi eſt, vile eſt:</hi> we alwaies eſteeme the worſt of that wee inioy: <hi>praeſentium taedio futuri deſiderio labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus,</hi> wee are ſick alwayes of the preſent, and for future things: <hi>tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius bona quàm mala ſenſimus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> wee are more ſenſible of ill then good, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith of his <hi>Terentia,</hi> that till he was exilde from her company, hee neuer knew what content it brought vnto him; wee neuer know what pleaſures are, till we bee berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of them: widdowers can onely iudge of the comfort of a wife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That Children are moſt obliged to their mothers.</head>
               <p>EDucing, education, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are the threefold cords that ſhould tye each childe to the loue of its mother: firſt, by educing or indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1255:29"/>to this world; wherin euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is as a good Land-Lord to her childe, giuing it both houſe-roome and nutriment, when it, like an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Tenant, doth grieue and vexe her, and, which is againſt the Leaſe of equity, many times cuts and crops the flouriſhing trees of their beauty, and growne too great for their places, as many mens minds are for their eſtates, they ſeeke for a more ample habitation, neither can they haue the Lawyers <hi>bene deceſsit,</hi> for many times <hi>(Proh dolor)</hi> they rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in their departure, their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, and yet women ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the trueſt louers, they loue them that hurt them; &amp; that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not to beginne a good action at all, then to deſiſt; hauing begunne, they perſeuere in their benefits, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them that <hi>alter a natura,</hi> that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature, education, nouriſhing our bodies as the Pellicane, though
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1255:30"/>not with the bloud, yet with the ſubſtance of their breſts, and when they are able inſtruments to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the faculties of the ſoule, they (and <hi>id maximum beneficium, quod animum reddit meliorem;</hi> that is the greateſt benefit which perfects the ſoule) ſuckle our mindes with the milke of good manners, train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs vp,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as <hi>Tanaquill</hi> did her ſonne, in religion and learning. The two <hi>Gracchi</hi> reaped all the flowers of their Oratory, from the Garden of their mothers vertues.
<note place="margin">Sucto.</note> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his eloquence by conuerſing with his mother. And <hi>Socrates,</hi> that Athenian Eagle, exhauſted all his wiſedome from the well-ſpring of <hi>Diol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nna's</hi> inſtructions.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Laſtly, by their affection. <hi>Rutilia</hi> followed her ſonne <hi>Cotta</hi> in his exile; and yet when death bereaued her of him, her eyes neuer ſhewed, her heart lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him, in <hi>expulſo virtutem oſtendit,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1255:30"/>in amiſso, prudentiam:</hi> in his exile ſhe ſhewed her loue, in his death, her wiſdome. Two Roman Matrons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding their ſons,
<note place="margin">Petrar. de Mater.</note> whom they dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue bin ſlaine in the great battel at <hi>Thraceninus,</hi> their ſoules as incapable of ſo inexpected ioy, took leaue of their bodies. But I need not induce Inſtances, ſince they are oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with <hi>Niobe</hi> &amp; <hi>Satyrus</hi> for ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for not louing them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. Two reaſons may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, why they doe moſt affect their children. Firſt, becauſe they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they are theirs. VVherfore <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> being asked, if it were true that <hi>Vliſſes</hi> was his father? anſwered, <hi>Mater quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta hoc dicit,</hi> My mother ſaith he was. Secondly, for that they haue moſt ſorrow by them: for <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis amat beneficia ſua,</hi> wee loue that moſt dearely, that coſts vs deareſt. There is one honour (ſaith <hi>Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tle</hi>) due to the father, another to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1255:31"/>mother: we owe moſt honour to our father in a Geometricall proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in reſpect of dignitie, but moſt to our mother in an Arithmeticall proportion, in reſpect of deſert. For we haue of them principally,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, our eſſence: Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, our nouriſhment: thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, our education: and <hi>amor, amoris magnes eſt, &amp; durus eſt, qui amorem non repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit:</hi> Loue is the Loadſtone of Loue, and hee is the moſt obdure, that doth not repay it. There is no ingratitude comparable to that which is committed againſt the mother. Euery man may ſay with <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Quicquid praeſtiti, infra aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem materni muneris eſt.</hi> When I haue performed all that I can, I can neuer recompence her. For hee is neuer conquered in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, whoſe benefit it is, that he is conquered. I will winde vp the clue of this Tract, with that patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1255:31"/>ſaying of <hi>Petrarch:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petrar. de Mater.</note>
                  <q>
                     <l>Cum nihil ſit natis</l>
                     <l>materno magis amore:</l>
                     <l>Iam mater ſtudijs</l>
                     <l>eſt veneranda pijs.</l>
                     <l>Since Mothers most</l>
                     <l>their childrens ſtates doe tender:</l>
                     <l>By obſequious dutie,</l>
                     <l>we them thankes ſhould render.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Caſtrophe.</head>
               <p>IT is no maruell if the <hi>Catharri</hi> would rechange three or foure men,
<note place="margin">Diod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for one woman captiuated or taken priſoner: if the Egyptians, &amp; Lycians, would haue them rule both in publike, and priuate: If the Lacedemonians called their wiues <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ladies:
<note place="margin">Tacide M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> If the Germans paid ſo deare for their Spouſes: If <hi>Plat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> held a woman as neceſſary in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, as a King in a Countrey; ſince they doe excell in all the principall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1255:32"/>paſſions of the minde; hauing, as <hi>Muſeus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Hero,</hi> a hundred graces: In continencie, <hi>Cato's;</hi> in fortitude, <hi>Scipio's;</hi> in conſtancie, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chates;</hi> in pulchritude, as the Poet ſaith of <hi>Amarintha,</hi> all beauty; in wit, the Marmulade and ſucket of Muſes: Cordial Nepenthes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to their husbands: True Pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans to their children. If Nature, ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> would ſee her ſelfe, woman muſt be her perſpectiue, or Looking-glaſſe? Women? What are they? Natures pride, Vertues ornament, Angels on earth, Saints in Heauen; memorable to be regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, worthy to bee ſerued. In a word, if the world bee a Ring, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is the Diamond ſet in this Ring.</p>
               <p>And now my Pen will needs take his leaue of its faire Loue, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, with blubbering, as you ſee theſe ruder teares of Inke. I may ſay,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1255:32"/>as <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſaith of himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Feſtus hiſt. Rom. init.</note> 
                  <hi>Res geſtas ſignaut, non ſcripſi,</hi> I haue touched, not handled their vertues. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue obſerued halfe of <hi>Aeſops</hi> counſel to <hi>Solon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lubin in Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that his ſpeech ſhould bee either ſhort, or ſweet. VVhat I want in ſuauitie, I haue endeuoured to ſupply by bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie: of which, if any one accuſe me, let <hi>Seneca</hi> giue a pricke to their Toade-ſwolne galls with his <hi>Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam parum eſt, quod ſatis eſt.</hi> I know, that more may be ſaid of each qualitie; but I deſired not to ſay all, but enough.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
